Finding Aid for Rensis Likert papers, 1929-1983.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rensis Likert papers
1929-1983
Likert, Rensis, 1903-
85514 Aa 2
Social scientist, director of the Institute for Social Research of the University of Michigan. Papers include project files, survey research data and reports, and printed material, largely from his work with the Division of Program Surveys, Bureau of Agricultural Economics and the office of War Information during World War II; Office Of Strategic Bombing Survey, I.S.R. project files; and transcript of oral interview, 1970.
27 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 5109 ) was first accessioned in 1975. Periodic additions have been received since then. 5109
The collection is open to research.
Rensis Likert was born August 5, 1903 in Cheyenne, Wyoming. He received his B.A. in chemical engineering from the University of Michigan in 1926, and his Ph.D. in social psychology from Columbia University in 1932. At Columbia, Likert worked under Gardner Murphy and first did work in measuring attitudes. After a period as an instructor of psychology and later assistant professor at New York University, Likert became director of research for the Life Insurance Agency Management Association of Hartford, Connecticut, working in this capacity from December 1935 to September 1939.
In September 1939, following a reorganization of the U.S. Department of Agriculture, Likert was selected to administer the Division of Program Surveys in the Bureau of Agricultural Economics (BAE), serving from 1939 to October 1946. His overall responsibility was the development of more scientific opinion surveys, and in this capacity, he and his staff conducted interviews which were at first concerned with problems of agricultural production and management, but which broadened out with World War II into studies of citizen morale and problems of the home front. While with BAE, Likert also conducted specialized surveys for the Office of War Information (OWI), the U.S. Department of Treasury, and the Federal Reserve Board. He also served during the latter stages of World War II as director of the Morale Division of the U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey, serving from November 1944 to June 1946.
With the conclusion of the war and a decline in government support, Likert began looking for a university setting where he and his staff could continue to do their research and conduct surveys on theoretical and social problems. The University of Michigan was selected, and on July 1, 1946, the Survey Research Center was established. In 1948 the Research Center for Group Dynamics left M.I.T. to join the University of Michigan. The combined organization became known as the Institute for Social Research (ISR). Likert served as director of the Survey Research Center from its founding in 1946 until he assumed the directorship of the new Institute for Social Research. He remained as director of ISR until his retirement in 1970.
In 1971, Likert formed a private consulting firm, Rensis Likert Associates, Inc. (RLA). The firm located its headquarters in Ann Arbor and established regional offices across the nation. RLA studied management styles and management systems in conjunction with survey research. The success of the firm stemmed from its utilization of Likert's Systems 1-4, which recognized and identified patterns of management, aiding businesses in achieving the most beneficial system of management.
Summary Contents List
Biographical Material, including transcripts of oral interviews [Box 1]
Bureau of Agricultural Economics [Boxes 1-8, 23-24] Bureau History and Related Materials [Box 1] Reports and Memoranda, 1939-1949 [Boxes 1-5; 23; 24] Background Files [Boxes 5-8, 23] Administrative Files [Box 23] Survey Research [Box 23] Methodology [Box 23] Division of Program Surveys [Box 23-24]
Office of War Information [Boxes 9-11] Reports and Memoranda [Boxes 9-10, 11] Survey of Intelligence Materials [Box 10] Intelligence Reports [Box 10] Miscellaneous files [Box 11] Administrative files [Box 11]
U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey [Boxes 11-13] Department Reports [Box 11-12] Miscellaneous Reports and Documents [Box 12-13] Administrative [Box 13]
Institute for Social Research/Survey Research Center [Boxes 13-20] Background [Box 13] Project files [Box 13-17] Building Fund-Raising Campaign [Box 18] Correspondence [Boxes 18-19] Administrative and miscellaneous files [Boxes 19-20]
Early Career [Boxes 21] Psychological Corporation [Box 21] Newell-Emmett Company [Box 21] Life Insurance Sales Research Bureau [Box 21]
Association and Committee Activities [Box 21]
Rensis Likert and Associates [Box 22]
Published Works [Boxes 22; 26]
Miscellaneous Project Files [Box 27]
Photographs [Box 27]
The Rensis Likert Papers document his work as one of the pioneers of survey research, first with the Bureau of Agricultural Economics, then with the Office of War Information, Office of Strategic Bombing Surveys and finally at the University of Michigan's Survey Research Center and Institute for Social Research. The papers include biographical information on Likert; transcripts of oral history interviews with Likert; reports, background information, correspondence relating to various survey projects.
The Likert papers were received and initially processed in four accessions in 1975, 1982,1990 and 1995. Material in later accessions sometimes continued or complemented records series in prior accessions. The papers are boxed in an order that reflects the dates the accessions individual accessions were received. In this finding aid the disparate parts of series received in multiple accessions have been together to reflect the intellectual arrangement of the collection. As a result, the box-folder sequence in he contents listing are not always consecutive.
The materials in the 1975 accession (boxes 1-20) of the Rensis Likert Papers cover the period of 1939 to 1953 and largely concern Likert's work at the Bureau of Agricultural Economics and the Office of War Information during World War II and his subsequent work in the early development of the Survey Research Center.
In 1982 the family of Rensis Likert donated an additional three feet (boxes 21-23) of materials. Notable items in this accession concern Likert's work as assistant secretary and treasurer of the Psychological Corporation (1934-1935); consultant to the Newell-Emmett Company (1935); survey researcher with the Morale Division of the United States Strategic Bombing Survey unit (ca. 1944-1946); and activities with other professional organizations (ca. 1938-1949)
The third accession of the Likert papers (box 24-29) came from the library of the Institute of Social Research of the University of Michigan. The files pertain to all phases of Likert's professional career, and thus the researcher should use these papers in conjunction with the materials in the previous accessions. The final accession (box 29) was received form several sources.
Subjects:
African Americans.; Agriculture--United States.; Detroit (Mich.); Likert, Rensis, 1903-1981; Oral history.; Strikes and lockouts--Rubber industry--Ohio.; Social sciences--Research.; Social surveys.; United States. Bureau of Agricultural Economics. Division of Program Surveys.; United States. Office of War Information.; United States--Social life and customs--1918-1945.; United States Strategic Bombing Survey.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Japan.; Survey research.; United States Strategic Bombing Survey.; War damage--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical material
  Biographical includes clippings and transcripts of oral interviews conducted with Rensis Likert.
  - Transcripts of oral interviews, 1970; 1976; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bureau of Agricultural Economics
  The series Bureau of Agricultural Economics contains reports and memoranda created by the BAE. Both rural and urban topics are covered in the pre-war reports and memoranda. Topics during the war years include studies on rationing, production, labor, and war loan drives. The reports are arranged chronologically and contain occasional background files relating to a specific report or study.
  - Bureau History and Related Materials
    - Lists of reports and studies (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Division history and related materials (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Survey research (general) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Survey research (methodology) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reports and memoranda
    - 1930
      - "The Institute of Methods of Rural Sociological Research," Summary Report (Box 24)
    - 1939
      - Current Opinion of Farmers, 9/23/1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Report on Farmer Attitudes, 10/17/1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1940
      - Rural and Urban Reactions to Conservation Work (Rough draft, exploratory study), 4/1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Report on Attitudes of Urban Residents Toward the Food Stamp Plan and Toward Alternative Methods of Disposing of Agricultural Surpluses, 4/29/1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Attitudes Toward the War and Its Expected Effects on Agriculture (War Report II), 5/15/1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Attitudes Toward the War and Its Expected Effects on Agriculture (Including material since invasion of Holland and Belgium). (War Report III), 5/24/1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - The Farmer Reports on: What things have made it hardest to get along on the farm? What things have helped most toward getting along on the farm?, 7/08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Attitudes of Farmers toward Equality of AAA Benefits (Preliminary Report), 7/10/1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Attitudes of Farmers toward Adequacy of Soil Conservation in Farm Programs (Preliminary Report), 7/11/1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Exploratory Study of Farmers' Attitudes Toward Administration of AAA (Preliminary report, 7/11/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - County Summary: LaSalle Co., Ill.; Delaware Co., Ind, 8/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Farmers' Reactions toward the Stamp Plan; Some preliminary results for Illinois and Indiana, 8/28/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward War, Defense and their Expected Effects on Agriculture; most recent preliminary results for Illinois and Indiana, 8/28/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Regional Summary; Recent Program Surveys, Illinois and Indiana, 8/28/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Farm Men's Cooperativeness Toward Programs; Preliminary results for Illinois and Indiana, 8/29/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Farmers' Attitudes toward Problems of Growing Tenancy; Preliminary results including recent material from Illinois and Indiana, 8/29/1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Farmers Discuss their Major Credit Problems and Role of Government in Farm Credit (Preliminary Report), 9/05/1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward Continuance of AAA and Need to Adjust it to War Development, 9/23/1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Reactions to the Land Use Planning Program of Farmers in Unified Counties, 9/30/1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Regional summaries of "Attitudes of Farm Men toward the War and Its Expected Effects on Agriculture", September-October 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - The Farmer Reports on: What things have made it hardest to get along on the farm? What things have helped most toward getting along on the farm? for Kansas, 10/08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - The Farmer Reports on: What things have made it hardest to get along on the farm? What things have helped most toward getting along on the farm? for North Dakota and Macon County, Missouri, 10/08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Eight months of Change in Farmers' Reactions to the War and Its Expected Effects on Agriculture Part I: General Summary, 10/15/1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Farmers' Reactions to The Stamp Plan, 10/26/1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Proposal for Study of Farmers' Reactions to the Administrative Operation of Farm Programs (Preliminary Draft), 11/29/1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Memorandum; Subject: Farmers' Reactions to the Administrative Operation of Farm Programs, 11/08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Preliminary Report on Exploratory Study of Farmers' Attitudes Toward Market Milk Order and Recent Referenda, 2/15/1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Untitled Manuscript (Kisatchie National Forest) (Box 24)
    - 1941
      - The New York Milk Market Order and Referenda, 2/22/1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - First Rough Draft of the AAA Study, 2/26/1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Preliminary Tabulations on Farmers' Reactions to a Suggested Production Control Program Featuring High Commodity Loans, 3/03/1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Agricultural Adjustment Administration Study, 3/11/1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - The General Reactions of Farmers to the AAA Program, 3/31/1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Farmers' Reactions to Possible Changes in the AAA Program with the Purpose of Encouraging Live-at-Home, 04/08/1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Responses to Some Questions on Nutrition, 5/1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Farmers' Opinions Concerning "Fair" Prices and Loan Rates for Corn, Wheat and Cotton, 05/01/1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - What Problems are Farmers Most Concerned About Today?, 5/09/1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Some Trends and Problems in Agriculture Today; A Discussion of Questions Asked at the "Agriculture Quiz Corner.", 6/1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Range of Spontaneous Suggestions Made by Farmers for Improving Specific Parts of the AAA Program, 06/13/1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Farmers' Expectations Regarding The War's Effect on Agriculture, Fall 1940-Spring 1941; 6/18/1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Special Defense Estimates for 1942, 6/20/1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - The Quiz Corner As a New Informational Technique, 7/1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Preliminary Comments on Mr. Rowalt's "Memorandum for the Administrative Council", 7/07/1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - New York Farmer Committeeman and the ACP, 8/26/1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Special Memorandum no. 1 on Current Situation--Farmers' Reactions Relative to the Department of Agriculture's Defense Plans, 08/1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Special Memorandum no. 2 on Current Situation--Farmers' Reactions Relative to the Department of Agriculture's Defense Plans, 9/08/1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Special Memorandum no. 3 on Current Situation--Farmers' Reactions Relative to the Department of Agriculture's Defense Plans, 9/01/1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Special Memorandum no. 4 on Current Situation--Farmers' Reactions Relative to the Department of Agriculture's Defense Plans, 9/22/1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Special memorandum no. 5 on Current Situation--Southern Farmers and the Defense Plans of The Department of Agriculture, 9/29/1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Attitudes of Farmers Toward Cheaper Medical Service in Farm Areas Through Some Form of Government Aid, 9/30/1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Wisconsin Dairy Farmers' Reactions to the Present Dairy Situation, 10/02/1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Eight Months of Change in Farmers' Reactions to the War and Its Expected Effects on Agriculture, Part I: General Summary, 10/15/1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Farmers and the Price Situation, 10/22/1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Reconnaissance Study of Wisconsin Dairy Situation Before Production Goals Campaign (Preliminary Report), 10/23/1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Local Civilian Defense in Relation to Other Urban Problems, 10/23/1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - The Wisconsin Production Goals Campaign in Action, 10/27/1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Reconnaissance Study of Pennsylvania Dairy Situation Before Production Goals Campaign (Preliminary Report), 11/19/1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Some Attitudes Toward Nutrition Problems in Five Large Cities, 11/19/1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - "Employee Morale in the Administrative Office, Bureau of Agricultural Economics" (Box 24)
    - 1941-1943
      - Rural Life Studies "The Culture of Contemporary Rural Communities"
        - Study 1 "El Cerrito, New Mexico" (Box 24)
        - Study 2 "Sublette, Kansas" (Box 24)
        - Study 3 "Landaff, New Hampshire" (Box 24)
        - Study 4 "The Old Older Amish of Lancaster County, Pennsylvania" (Box 24)
        - Study 5 "Irwin, Iowa" (Box 24)
        - Study 6 "Harmony, Georgia" (Box 24)
    - 1942
      - Preview of the 1942 Production Situation: Highlights of the Field Survey, 3/25/1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Preview of 1942 Production Situation: Summary of results of a survey made by the Bureau in March 1942 4/1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Farmers Look at the Post-War Period, 05/29/1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - United Dairy Farmers Union Issue in Michigan, 6/27/1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Confidential Material Prepared for the Meeting of War Board Fieldmen: Part I, 407/08/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Confidential Material Prepared for the Meeting of War Board Fieldmen: Part III, 7/08/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Baldwin County, Alabama, 7/10/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Confidential Material Prepared for the Meeting of War Board Fieldmen: Part II, 7/13/1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Copiah County, Mississippi, 7/13/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Yolo County, California, 7/16/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Yellowstone County, Montana, 7/20/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Scotts Bluff County, Nebraska, 7/20/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Bingham County, Idaho, 7/23/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Davis County, Utah, 7/28/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation Buffalo County, Nebraska, 7/31/1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Manpower in Agriculture for 1943, 8/12/1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the United States Employment Service, 8/14/1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Labor Situation in Southeastern Truck Farming Areas, 8/21/1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Attitudes of Farmers Toward Setting of Production Goals on Individual Farms, 8/22/1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Farmers Attitudes Toward the 1942 Peanut Harvest--Bryan and Creek Counties, Oklahoma, 8/24/1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - The Labor Situation in the Peach Harvest, Sutter and Yuba Counties, California, 8/28/1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Memorandum No. 62: Rural Life Trends, a memorandum on plans and procedures, 9/15/1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - The Farm Labor Situation in the Apricot Harvest, Santa Clara County, California, 9/25/1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Farmers' Intentions in Regard to Dairy Production for 1943 -1), 10/03/1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - The Farm Labor Situation in the Midwest -2), 10/19/1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Disposal of Dairy Cattle in the Midwest -3), 10/19/1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Farmers' Production Plans for Vegetable Oils During 1943 Part I: Soybeans C-4), 11/23/1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Farmers' Production Plans for Vegetable Oils During 1943, Part II: Peanuts C-5), 11/23/1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Farmers Production Plans for Vegetable Oils During 1943, Part III: Flax C-6), 11/23/1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Farmers' Views on Production Plans of Soybeans, Peanuts, and Flax for 1943 (Preliminary Report), 11/23/1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Memorandum: Summary of Material on Economic Expectations about the Post-war World (based on data from Studies 51, 52 and 53), 10/30/1942 (Box 23)
      - Dairy Farmers Look at the Labor Problem and Proposed "Solutions" C-7), 11/28/1942 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Participation in War Savings Program (Preliminary Report), 12/24/1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Saving and Spending in Buffalo: Second Study, 12/24/1942 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Participation in the War Savings Program. Supplementary Report I: Public Attitudes with Respect to Spending or Saving (Preliminary Report), Study No. 55; Report No. 33, 12/29/1942 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Participation in the War Savings Program. Supplementary Report II: How Would the Public React to Compulsory Bond Buying? Study No. 55; Report No. 34, 12/30/1942 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Saving and Spending in Buffalo: (Second Run). Study No. S/71; Special Report No. 31, 12/30/1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Participation in the War Savings Program. Supplementary Report III: Reactions to Current Types of Promotional Appeal. Study No. 55; Report No. 35, 12/30/1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Program Survey Reports, 1941-1942; 1 volumes (Box 24)
      - Memoranda from Ruth Tolman (BAE Head) (Box 24)
      - Kurt Lewin Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Study S-72, "The Social Dynamics of Detroit,", 1942 (Box 25)
    - 1942-1946
      - Program Surveys Newsletters (Box 24)
    - 1943
      - Study of Dealers Attitudes Towards Gas Rationing in Detroit (Exploratory Study), Study No. R/5; Special Report No. 33, 1/02/1943 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Farmers and the Food Production Program. Study No. A/4; Report No. C-8, 1/02/1943 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Saving and Spending in Buffalo: Second Study, Study No. S-71; Special Report 31, 1/06/1943 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Participation in the War Savings Program. Supplementary Report I: Public Attitudes with Respect to Spending or Saving. Study No. 55; Report No. 33, 01/06/1943
      - The Victory Tax and Payroll Deduction of Bonds, Study No. 59; Report No. 36, 1/07/1943 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Retailers Reactions to Food Rationing and Shortages in Detroit (Exploratory Study), Study No. R/5; Special Report No. 32, 1/08/1943
      - Reactions to Current Appeals in the Sale of War Bonds (Memorandum), Study No. 55, 1/08/1943 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Farmers and the Food Production Program Section I: The Farmers' Reaction to the Program as a Whole. Study A-4; Report C-8, 1/12/1943 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Farmers and the Food Production Program Section II: The Administration of the Program. Study A-4; Report C-9, 1/12/1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Use of Japanese Evacuees as Farm Labor: Sugar Beet and Long Staple Cotton Regions (Preliminary Report), Study A-3, 1/15/1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Attitudes Toward Cheese Rationing: with Notes on Attitudes Toward Substitutes for Meat, Milk and Butter, Study A-5; Report C-10, 1/16/1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Memorandum: Factors Involved in Preparation for Income Tax Payments, 1/22/1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Some data on Farmers' Attitudes Toward: The Labor Situation in the Long Staple Cotton Area in the Southwest, Study A-3; Report No. C-11, 1/23/1943 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Memorandum: The Farmers' Participation in the War Savings Program, Study No. 55, 1/26/1943 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Farmers' Attitudes Toward the Use of Japanese Evacuees as Farm Labor, Part I: Sugar Beet and Long Staple Cotton Regions; Study A-3 Report No. C-12, 1/30/1943 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Memorandum [1-49], 2/01/1943
      - Farmers and the Food Production Program, Section III: Special Supplement on Colorado and Idaho Counties, Study A-4; Report C-13, 2/10/1943 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - The Labor Problem as Seen by Farm Operators in Michigan (Saginaw County) and Ohio (Medina County), Study A/3; Report No. C-14, 2/12/1943 (Box 1, Folder 50)